A Disclaimer

Before I begin, I have to admit that this chapter is mostly based on the material from a series of posts by Scot Bain and Amir Kolsky from the blog Sustainable Test Driven Development and their upcoming book by the same title. I like their idea of boundaries so much that I just follow the guidelines they outlined. This chapter is going to be a rephrase of these guidelines. I placed it here so that you have all the important topics covered in one place, but I encourage you to read the original blog posts on this subject on http://www.sustainabletdd.com (and the upcoming book).

Specifying Boundaries and Conditions

Sometimes, Anonymous Value Is Not Enough

When we specify a behavior, there are times when this behavior should be the same no matter what arguments we pass to the constructor or invoked methods. An example would be an addition of two numbers - whatever numbers we would supply, the answer would always be a sum of those numbers:

[Fact] public void
ShouldCalculateTheSumOfTwoNumbers()
{
  //GIVEN
  var a = Any.Integer();
  var b = Any.Integer();

  //WHEN
  var result = new Sum().Of(a, b);

  //WHEN
  Assert.Equal(a + b, result);
}

In this case, the integer numbers can really be “any” - the described relationship between input and output is independent of the actual values we use. As indicated in one of the previous chapters, this is the canonical case where Constrained Non-Determinism applies.

Sometimes, however, objects exhibit different behaviors based on what is passed to their constructor and to their methods (OK, we also have static methods and singletons. Longer discussion on those will be included in one of the next chapters - for now we can safely ignore them). For example, in our application we may have a licensing policy where a feature is allowed to use only if the license is valid, and denied after it has expired. Another example would be that some shops are open from 10:00 to 18:00, so if we had a query in our application whether the shop is currently open, we would expect it to be answered differently based on what the current time is.

In such cases, Scott and Amir offer us other guidelines for choosing input values.

Exceptions To The Rule

There are times, when a Statement is true for every value except one (or more) explicitly specified. For example, in Poland, high school students are graded for exams between “mediocre” and “very good”. Every grade means the exam is passed except for “mediocre” grade which means the exam is failed. If we imagine we have to specify an object that decides whether the exam is passed based on rating, we would have to write two Statements: one for the mediocre rating and other for all the others.

Here is the Statement for mediocre grade (let us imagine that all grades are members of an enum):

[Fact] public void
ShouldNotPassTheExamWhenGradeIsMediocre()
{
  //GIVEN
  var decision = new PassOrNotDecision();

  //WHEN
  var examPassed = decision.MakeBasedOn(Grades.Mediocre);

  //THEN
  Assert.False(examPassed);
}

Note that here, we used the literal value of Grades.Mediocre. This is because no other value gives the same behavior as this one, so generating the value would not make any sense.

The second Statement is for all the other cases. Here, we are going to use another method of the Any class for generating ay enum member other than specified:

[Fact] public void
ShouldPassTheExamWhenGradeIsOtherThanMediocre()
{
  //GIVEN
  var decision = new PassOrNotDecision();

  //WHEN
  var examPassed 
    = decision.MakeBasedOn(Any.Besides(Grades.Mediocre));

  //THEN
  Assert.True(examPassed);
}

Here, Any.Besides() takes care of the enum value generation, producing a nice, readable code as a side effect.

The example shown above assumes there is only one exception to the rule (the mediocre grade). However, this concept can be scaled up to more values, as long as it is a finished, discrete set. If there are multiple exceptional values that produce the same behavior, a single Statement is sufficient to cover them all (using Any class and making the following call for exception Statement: Any.Of(value1, value2) and the following for the rest: Any.OtherThan(value1, value2)). However, when there are multiple exceptions to the rule and each one triggers a different behavior, each one deserves its own Statement.

Rules Valid Within Boundaries

Sometimes, a behavior varies around a numerical boundary. the simplest example would be a set of rules on how to calculate an absolute value of a number:

for any X less than 0, the result is -X (e.g. absolute value of -1.5 is 1.5)
for any X greater or equal to 0, the result is X (e.g. absolute value of 3 is 3).

As you can see, there is a boundary between the two behaviors and the right edge of the boundary is 0. Why do I say “right edge”? That is because the boundary always has two edges and there’s a length between them. If we assume we are talking about the mentioned absolute value calculation and that our numerical domain is that of integer numbers, we can as well use -1 as edge value and say that:

for any X less or equal to -1, the result is -X (e.g. absolute value of -1.5 is 1.5)
for any X greater than -1, the result is X (e.g. absolute value of 3 is 3).

So a boundary is not a single number - it always has a length - the length between last value of the previous behavior and the first value of the next behavior. In case of our example, the length between -1 (left edge - last negated number) and 0 (right edge - first non-negated) is 1.

Now, imagine that we are not talking about integer values anymore, but about floating point values. Then the right edge value would still be 0. But what about left edge? It would not be possible for it to stay -1, because the rule applies to e.g. -0.9 as well. So what is the correct right edge value and the correct length of the boundary? Would the length be 0.1? Or 0.001? Or maybe 0.00000001? This is harder to answer and depends heavily on the context, but it is something that must be answered for each particular case - this way we know what kind of precision is expected of us. In our Specification, we have to document the boundary length somehow.

So the next topic is: how to describe the boundary length with Statements? To illustrate this, I want to show you two Statements assuming we’re implementing the mentioned absolute value calculation for integers. The first Statement is for values smaller than 0 and we want to use the left edge value here ilke this:

[Fact] public void
ShouldNegateTheNumberWhenItIsLessThan0()
{
  //GIVEN
  var function = new AbsoluteValueCalculation();
  var lessThan0 = 0 - 1;

  //WHEN
  var result = function.PerformFor(lessThan0);

  //THEN
  Assert.Equal(-lessThan0, result);
}

And the next Statement for values at least 0 and we want to use the right edge value:

[Fact] public void
ShouldNotNegateTheNumberWhenItIsGreaterOrEqualTo0()
{
  //GIVEN
  var function = new AbsoluteValueCalculation();
  var moreOrEqualTo0 = 0;

  //WHEN
  var result = function.PerformFor(moreOrEqualTo0);

  //THEN
  Assert.Equal(moreOrEqualTo0, result);
}

There are two things to note about these examples. The first one is that we don’t use any kind of Any methods. We explicitly take the edges, because they’re the numbers that most strictly define the boundary. This way we document the boundary length.

It is important to understand why we are not using methods like Any.IntegerGreaterOrEqualTo(0), even though we do use Any in case when we have no boundary. This is because in the latter case, no value is better than the other in any particular way. In case of boundaries, however, the edge values are better in that they more strictly define the boundary and drive the right implementation.

The second thing to note is the usage of literal constant 0 in the above example. In one of the previous chapter, I showed you a technique called Constant Specification, where we write an explicit Statement about the value of the named constant and use the named constant everywhere else instead of its literal. So why did i not use this technique?

The only reason is that this might have looked a little bit silly with such extremely trivial example as calculating absolute value. In reality, I should have used the named constant in both Statements and it would show the boundary length even more clearly. Actually, let use perform this exercise now and see what happens.

First, let us document the named constant:

[Fact] public void
ShouldIncludeSmallestValueNotToNegateSetToZero()
{
  Assert.Equal(0, Constants.SmallestValueNotToNegate);
}

Now we have got everything we need to rewrite the two Statements we wrote earlier. The first would look like this:

[Fact] public void
ShouldNegateTheNumberWhenItIsLessThanSmallestValueNotToNegate()
{
  //GIVEN
  var function = new AbsoluteValueCalculation();
  var lastNumberToNegate 
    = Constants.SmallestValueNotToNegate - 1;

  //WHEN
  var result = function.PerformFor(lastNumberToNegate);

  //THEN
  Assert.Equal(-lastNumberToNegate, result);
}

And the second Statement for values at least 0:

[Fact] public void
ShouldNotNegateNumberWhenItIsGreaterOrEqualToSmallestValueNotToNegate()
{
  //GIVEN
  var function = new AbsoluteValueCalculation();

  //WHEN
  var result = function.PerformFor(
    Constants.SmallestValueNotToNegate
  );

  //THEN
  Assert.Equal(
    Constants.SmallestValueNotToNegate, result);
}

As you can see, the first Statement contains the following expression: Constants.SmallestValueNotToNegate - 1, where 1 is the exact length of the boundary. Like I said, the situation is so trivial that it may look silly and funny, however, in real life scenarios, this is a great technique to apply anytime, anywhere.

Boundaries may look like they apply only to integer input, but they occur at many other places. There are boundaries associated with date/time (e.g. an action is performed again when time from last action is at least 30 seconds - the decision would need to be made whether we need precision in seconds or maybe in ticks), to strings (e.g. validation of user name where it must be at least 2 characters, or password that must contain at least 2 special characters) etc.

Combination of Boundaries - Ranges

So, what about a behavior that is valid in a range? Let us assume that we live in a country where a citizen can get a driving license only after their 17th birthday, but before 65th (the government decided that people after 65 have worse sight and it’s safer not to give them new driving licenses). Let us also assume that we try to develop a class that answers the question whether we can apply for driving license and the return values of this query are as follows:

Age < 17 - returns enum value QueryResults.TooYoung
17 <= age >= 65 - returns enum value QueryResults.AllowedToApply
Age > 65 - returns enum value QueryResults.TooOld

Now, remember I told you that we specify the behaviors near boundaries? This, however, when applied to the situation I just described, would give us the following Statements:

Age = 17, should yield result QueryResults.TooYoung
Age = 18, should yield result QueryResults.AllowedToApply
Age = 65, should yield result QueryResults.AllowedToApply
Age = 66, should yield result QueryResults.TooOld

thus, we would describe the behavior where the query should return AllowedToApply value twice, which effectively means that we would copy-paste the Statement and change just one value. How do we deal with this? Thankfully, we have a solution available:

Most xUnit frameworks provide some kind of data-driven test functionality, which we can use to write parameterized Statements. The functionality basically means that we can write the code of the Statement once, but make the xUnit framework invoke it twice with different sets of input values. Let’s see an example in XUnit.net:

[Theory]
[InlineData(17, QueryResults.TooYoung)]
[InlineData(18, QueryResults.AllowedToApply)]
[InlineData(65, QueryResults.AllowedToApply)]
[InlineData(66, QueryResults.TooOld)]
public void ShouldYieldResultForAge(int age, QueryResults expectedResult)
{
  //GIVEN
  var query = new DrivingLicenseQuery();

  //WHEN
  var result = query.ExecuteFor(age);

  //THEN
  Assert.Equal(expectedResult, result);
}

This way, there is only one Statement executed four times. The case of AllowedToApply is still evaluated twice for both edge cases (so there is more time spent on executing it, which for small cases is not an issue), but the code maintenance issue is gone - we don’t have to copy-paste the code to specify both edges of the behavior.

Note that we’re quite lucky because the specified logic is strictly functional (i.e. returns different results based on different inputs). Thanks to this, we could parameterize input values together with expected results. This is not always the case. For example, let us imagine that we have a clock class where we can set alarm time. The class allows us to set hour between 0 and 24, but otherwise throws an exception.

While some xUnit frameworks, like NUnit, allow us to handle both cases with one Statement by writing something like this:

//NOTE: this is an example in NUnit framework!
[TestCase(Hours.Min, Result=Hours.Min)]
[TestCase(Hours.Max, Result=Hours.Max)]
[TestCase(Hours.Min-1, ExpectedException = typeof(OutOfRangeException))]
[TestCase(Hours.Max+1, ExpectedException = typeof(OutOfRangeException))]
public int 
ShouldBeAbleToSetHourBetweenMinAndMaxButNotOutsideThatRange(
  int inputHour)
{
  //GIVEN
  var clock = new Clock();
  clock.SetAlarmHour(inputHour);

  //WHEN
  var setHour = clock.GetAlarmHour();

  //THEN
  return setHour;
}

Others, like XUnit.NET, don’t (not that it’s a defect of the framework, it’s just that the philosophy behind those two is a little bit different and that some features have hidden price attached to their usage which some frameworks are willing to pay, while others aren’t). Thus, we have to solve it by writing two parameterized Statements - one where a value is returned (for valid cases) and one where exception is thrown (for invalid cases). The first would look like this:

[Theory]
[InlineData(Hours.Min)]
[InlineData(Hours.Max)]
public void 
ShouldBeAbleToSetHourBetweenMinAndMax(int inputHour)
{
  //GIVEN
  var clock = new Clock();
  clock.SetAlarmHour(inputHour);

  //WHEN
  var setHour = clock.GetAlarmHour();

  //THEN
  Assert.Equal(inputHour, setHour);
}

and the second:

[Theory]
[InlineData(Hours.Min-1)]
[InlineData(Hours.Max+1)]
public void 
ShouldThrowOutOfRangeExceptionWhenTryingToSetAlarmHourOutsideValidRange(
  int inputHour)
{
  //GIVEN
  var clock = new Clock();

  //WHEN - THEN
  Assert.Throws<OutOfRangeException>( 
    ()=> clock.SetAlarmHour(inputHour)
  );
}

Summary

In this chapter, we covered specifying numerical boundaries with a minimal amount of code, so that the Specification is more maintainable and runs fast. There is one more kind of situation left: when we have compound conditions (e.g. a password must be at least 10 characters and contain at least 2 special characters) - we’ll get back to those when we introduce mocks.

Sorting Out The Bits

In the previous chapter, there has been a lively conversation between Johnny and Benjamin. Even in such a short session, Benjamin, as a TDD novice, had a lot of questions and a lot of things he needed sorted out. We will pick up all those questions and explain them one by one. Here they are:

How to name a Statement?
How to start writing a Statement?
How is TDD about analysis and what does this “GIVEN-WHEN-THEN” mean?
What exactly is the scope of a Statement? A class, a method, or something else?
What is the role of TODO list in TDD?
Why use anonymous generated values instead of literals as input of a specified behavior?
Why and how to use the Any class?
What code to extract from a Statement to shared utility method?
Why such a strange approach to create enumerated constants?

A lot of questions, isn’t it? It is unfortunate that TDD has this high entry barrier, at least for someone used to the traditional way of writing code. Anyway, that is what this tutorial is for - to answer such questions and lower this barrier. Thus, we will try to answer those questions one by one.

dependency injection?

What should be stable in your system?

What code to extract from a Statement to shared utility method?

Why such a strange approach to create enumerated constants?

TODO

Expanded TDD process

As a little introduction, I’ll show you an expanded version of TDD flow that we’ll be using:

Examine TODO list and pick an item that makes most sense to implement next
Write unfulfilled Statement
Make it unfulfilled for the right reason
Fulfill the Statement and make sure all already fulfilled Statements are still fulfilled
Cross out the item from TODO list
Repeat until no item is left on the TODO list

Some of the steps don’t probably mean anything to yet. Don’t worry, we’ll be reiterating them several times, so don’t try to memorize them now.

What exactly do we specify?

In this chapter, we’ll look a little bit on what it is that we actually write our specification against - what exactly do we want to describe about a class. We’re gonna jump into a quick example, because I’ve been keeping you away from practice too long now. Note that the example won’t exactly show how the real-world TDD looks like, but it will be enough to draw some conclusions and get a feel of Statement-First style of programming.

quick example (list? calculator?)

TODO - todo list

Although the idea of doing code kata to practice TDD is quite popular, I couldn’t get on this train for a long time. The reason was that I was striving to find a kata that would help me practice or demonstrate a mock-based TDD, at the same time being simple and showing all the testing categories, as well as test reflexology in practice.

This was until I ran into a situation that, with few simplifications, could be turned into a compelling kata to show off the power of mocks and Need-Driven Development.

I’ve decided to present the kata in a series of posts. This one is going to be about the challenge only.

The challenge

Imagine the following situations: you’re creating a message processing module for a system that receives data in a form of frames from the network. The frame parsing is done using a proprietary third party library and your module receives the frames as deserialized objects. As the class for the objects is stored in the third-party library, you cannot change it (e.g. add or remove methods or change any signature).

There is only one type of frame, described below:

public class Frame
{
  int Speed { get; set; }
  int Age { get; set; }
  string Sender { get; set; }
}

Your task is to implement the message processing. So far, it only consists of validation and nothing more. Each field of each incoming frame is validated. The following examples describe the validation rules:

type of field | Correctness criteria | When satisfied | When not satisfied
int | greater than 0 | do nothing | throw exception
string | not null and not empty | do nothing | throw exception

Of course, you have to do this test-first.

Two more posts to come - one for failure, one for success

I believe that failure and success are both great opportunities to learn something valuable. So in the next post, I’ll try to show you how to screw up :-) and what we can learn from the failure by listening to the tests.

In the meantime, you can try to solve the kata yourself (coming up with any solutions should be trivial) and share your observations.

Good night, everyone!

In one of my previous posts I promised, that I’d share with you some hints on reducing the cost of maintaining class mocks. Remember that I’m not recommending class mocks, just showing you what to do when you have little choice. That said, I’ll try to highlight a way to deal with constructor maintenance.

My plan is as follows: first, I’ll introduce the general pattern and describe its canonical use in unit testing. Then I’ll show you how adding one teeny tiny method drives us to the solution to our mock constructor issue.

The builder to the rescue!

Before we jump into creating mocks, let’s note that there are many unit tests where we create the specified object (e.g. in class X specifications, we create new object of class X in every spec/unit test, at least that’s what I do, since I strongly believe that Setup/Teardown are last resort mechanisms).

Now, just to let you get a feeling of what I’m talking about, let’s look at simple example:

[Test]
public void ShouldCopyFromSourceToDestination()
{
  //GIVEN
  var source = new Mock<ISource>();
  var destination = new Mock<IDestination>();
  var anyLog = Any.InstanceOf<ILog>();
  var anyFile = Any.InstanceOf<IFile>();  
  var copyOperation = new CopyOperation(source, destination, anyLog);
  source.Setup(m => m.Get()).Returns(anyFile);

  //WHEN
  copyOperation.PerformOn(anyFile);
  
  //THEN
  destination.Verify(m => m.Write(anyFile));
}

Let’s see - what does this logging object do here? It’s not really part of the behavior - it only makes the intent less visible! Also, when we add another parameter to the constructor, we’ll have to update all specs that create a CopyOperation object.

There are cases when having many constructor parameters is a sign that it’s high time to introduce a Facade in the design. But sometimes not. In such cases we can use a builder pattern that takes only the parameters that are important. No need for logger when we specify logging-agnostic behaviors. For example:

[Test]
public void ShouldCopyFromSourceToDestination()
{
  //GIVEN
  var source = new Mock<ISource>();
  var destination = new Mock<IDestination>();
  var anyFile = Any.InstanceOf<IFile>();  
  var copyOperation = new CopyOperationBuilder()
    .Source(source)
    .Destination(destination)
    .Build();
  
  source.Setup(m => m.Get()).Returns(anyFile);

  //WHEN
  copyOperation.PerformOn(anyFile);
  
  //THEN
  destination.Verify(m => m.Write(anyFile));
}

The implementation of such builder is dead simple:

public class CopyOperationBuilder()
{
  private ISource _source 
    = new Mock<ISource>().Object;
  private IDestination _destination 
    = new Mock<IDestination>().Object;
  private ILog _log 
    = new Mock<ILog>().Object;

  public CopyOperationBuilder Source(
    ISource source)
  {
    _source = source;
    return this;
  }

  public CopyOperationBuilder Destination(
    IDestination destination)
  {
    _destination = destination;
    return this;
  }

  public CopyOperationBuilder Log(ILog log)
  {
    _log = log;
    return this;
  }

  public CopyOperation Build()
  {
    return new CopyOperation(
      _source, 
      _destination, 
      _log);
  }
}

Easy, isn’t it? Not only did we make the specification more meaningful, we also made the spec less prone to changes in constructor - when new parameter is added that doesn’t affect the spec, the builder is the only place we need to update.

OK, now that I introduced the pattern and its usual usage in unit testing, let’s see how we can benefit from it in case of mocking.

Mock builder

Now, time for a trick. We can just add another method in the builder, that will build a mock for us:

public class CopyOperationBuilder
{
  //all the methods described above…

  public Mock<CopyOperation> BuildMock()
  {
    return new Mock<CopyOperation>(
      _source, 
      _destination, 
      _log) { CallBase = true };
  }
}

And that’s it. Simple and sweet trick that may become handy in those very rare cases where we need to create class mocks.

Good night everyone!

Thanks go to Grzegorz Sławecki for inspiration.

Exemplary problem

Imagine we’re in a different reality, where tests are written after the code. we have written the following code (by the way, it’s not perfect as an example of using WCF, but it’s out of scope of this post):

public class SendingFromBuffer
{
  Buffer _buffer;

  public SendingThroughBuffer(Buffer buffer)
  {
    _buffer = buffer;
  }
    
  public void Perform()
  {
    var destination = CreateDestination ();
    while (_buffer.HasPackets()) 
    {
      destination.Send (_buffer.GetPacket ());
    }
  }
    
  public Destination CreateDestination()
  {
    var binding = new BasicHttpBinding();
    var endpoint = new EndpointAddress(
      "http://localhost/MyService/Something");
    var channelFactory = new ChannelFactory<Destination>(
      binding, endpoint);
    return channelFactory.CreateChannel();
  }
}

And now we would like to write a unit test for it. In particular - for the sending logic.

Actually, we could do it easily if not for the result of CreateDestination() method. It’s a WCF channel, so sending anything through it without actually connecting to the server yields an exception. To execute the code as is, we would need set up a server and use the operating system networking capabilities and (remember!) we want to be isolated from the operating system as much as we can during unit test. Also setting up a WCF server impacts unit test performance, making it slower.

As the code wasn’t written test-first, it’s already untestable, so we’ll have to refactor it (wow, and imagine it was created just about an hour ago!) to isolate ourselves from the WCF channel. Thankfully, we have the channel creation encapsulated in its own method, so it’s very easy to extract it to a separate class and use dependency injection to inject either a real object or a mock into the SendingFromBuffer class.

After the refactoring, the code looks like this:

public class SendingFromBuffer
{
  Buffer _buffer;
  DestinationFactory _destinationFactory;

  public SendingThroughBuffer(
    Buffer buffer, DestinationFactory factory)
  {
    _buffer = buffer;
    _destinationFactory = factory;
  }
    
  public void Perform()
  {
    var destination = _destinationFactory.Create();
    while (_buffer.HasPackets()) 
    {
      destination.Send(_buffer.GetPacket ());
    }
  }
}

public interface DestinationFactory
{
  Destination Create();
}
  
public class WcfDestinationFactory : DestinationFactory
{
  public Destination Create()
  {
    var binding = new BasicHttpBinding();
    var endpoint = new EndpointAddress(
      "http://localhost/MyService/Something");
    var channelFactory = new ChannelFactory<Destination>(
      binding, endpoint);
    return channelFactory.CreateChannel();
  }
}

Note that we have introduced a factory object with one method that has just a few lines. this yields the two following questions:

Aren’t we introducing an unnecessary abstraction that bloats the design?
Aren’t we hurting readability with this additional object?

Let’s take those questions on one by one.

1. Aren’t we introducing an unnecessary abstraction that bloats the design?

Ok, think with me - is this factory really necessary? I mean, it’s just a few lines of code! Why the heck would we want to delegate that to a separate class?

Well, we do and I’ll tell you why. It’s because the reason for creating classes is not to move lines of code. You see, the goal of introducing all this object oriented stuff into programming languages in the first place was to enable us to do the following:

encapsulate something
loosen coupling
attain better cohesion
get rid of redundancy
make the class easier for testing (ok, this one came later, but it’s equally important)
enhance readability
provide a better chance for reuse

Do you see “lines of code” anywhere on this list? No? Good, because me neither :-). Well, maybe the readability part, but we’ll deal with that later. Sadly, this is a common myth that many junior programmers repeat endlessly - that the amount of lines of code is a criteria for something to be sealed inside a class or a method. The truth is, one can even introduce a class that doesn’t have ANY executable code (many Null Objects are implemented this way).

I mean, if we really don’t care about the things outlined above, we can just as well write everything in procedural style - who needs all these objects, classes, interfaces and stuff? No one, because they’re a design tool, not an implementation tool. And as “lines of code” is not a design quality, it has nothing to do with design.

So, let’s evaluate the decision to introduce a factory in the context of real design qualities described above, not those made up, like “lines of code”:

Encapsulation

Introduction of a factory encapsulates the knowledge on what library are we actually using for communication. By doing this, we can get rid of another “tiny bit of code”, that impacts this class significantly:

using System.ServiceModel;

you see, not having this line inside our class file frees us from dragging a heavy dependency around every time we want to reuse the class. This is a great benefit, since getting rid of such heavy dependencies enhances reuse.

Coupling

By decoupling the class from WCF, we open it for extensions - we can put in another factory that creates different implementation using another remote procedure call mechanism. We gain reuse and extensibility in return.

Cohesion

By getting the knowledge about creating communication channel away from the SendingFromBuffer class, we make it less prone to change, because any change in the way communication occurs does not impact this code. Cohesive classes make finding defects and issues very easy. E.g. When the app fails with WCF connection, we’ve got a very limited area to search for problems. We don’t have to wonder at all whether a code fulfilling another responsibility in the same class is affected by the WCF channel creation somehow or not.

Why do I think I have the right to say that the WCF part is a “separate responsibility”? Because there’s a strict boundary between this code and the rest of the class. Just look at the table below:

Question | Wcf part | The rest of the class
Need to unit test? | No * | Yes
Part of application domain logic? | No | Yes
Can be changed to allow easier unit testing? | No | Yes

* - well, I’d probably write a unit test to specify what parameters should be set on the channel after creation and that the created instance is not null, but I wouldn’t try to send anything through it.

So as you see, these two aspects of the class are different and hence should be separated.

Redundancy

Let’s assume that this isn’t the only place where we’re opening up a connection and sending a message through it. In such case, without the factory, we’d have to introduce a method for creating the channel in every class that needs it. Every time the logic for creating a channel changes, we have to make corrections in all of these methods. This is asking for trouble.

Testability

Using dependency injection and a factory opens the class for unit testing - which we wouldn’t be able to do otherwise. Of course, we could make the creation method virtual and override it in a subclass with a stub implementation, but is really more straightforward or less effort than the factory solution? By the way, TDD IS about design and analysis, so when a test tells you that you need an additional abstraction, then you do. That’s what you write the tests for - to discover them.

Readability

we’ll take care of it in a second.

Reuse

This is a result of all the other points. A class that is easy to reuse encapsulates its responsibility well, dooes not have accidential coupling, is very cohesive, does not include redundant aspects, is documented with set of simple and well-written unit tests that describe all its behaviors and is readable.

Ok, that pretty much represents my thinking on the issue, the only thing left is question number 2:

2. Aren’t we hurting readability with this additional object?

How do you define readability? Many people mistakenly think that readability is about looking at the code and being able to tell everything that happens from it - such code would make everything it does explicit. If so, then it would be best not to partition the code in any way, but just use a single function or a method that does all the stuff. Thinking this eay leads us to the conclusion that each time we’re introducing a method or a variable, we hurt readability, because things become less explicit. e.g. this:

int a = pow(2,2);

is less explicit than:

var a = 2*2;

And yet, we’d rather use the first form rather than the second, because it’s more intention-revealing (although the second does a better job in telling what actually happens).

So as you might have already guessed - for me, the main trait of readability is not explicitness. It’s revealing intentions.

Let’s take a look at the two following pieces of code:

public void Process(Frame frame)
{
  validation.PerformFor(frame);
  compression.PerformOn(frame);
  encryption.PerformOn(frame);
}

…and:

public void Process(Frame frame)
{
  if(frame.Destination == null)
  {
    throw new Exception();
  }
  
  for(int i = 0 ; i i < frame.NumberOfWords ; ++i)
  {
    var word = frame.Words[i];
    frame.Words[i] = word.Trim();
  }
  
  for(int i = 0 ; i i < frame.NumberOfWords ; ++i)
  {
    var word = frame.Words[i];
    frame.Words[i] = word.Reverse();
  }
}

Which one is more explicit? The second one, of course. Which is more readable? I’d argue that the first one - not only does it make clear what steps are performed, it also makes a point about their order. This is crucial, because encrypting a compressed content would give you a different result than compressing an encrypted content. If we’re sending the frame to any other system, it can probably interpret only one of these two options. That’s why the order is probably something that is enforced by requirements and it’s great that it’s reflected in the code.

By the way, one could argue, that we could just do this:

public void Process(Frame frame)
{
  validate(frame);
  compress(frame);
  encrypt(frame);
}

That’s true, although, when reading this code, I’d most probably jump into each of these methods to see what they do - after all, it’s the same class and I’m trying to grasp it. This forces me to get my head around more details than I need to, because everytime I’m reading this class, there is always “that other code”, that’s doing some fancy things and may modify some fields that may be used somewhere else. For example, how do I know that compression does not set a flag somewhere to trigger different encryption in the encrypt() method depending on the compression ratio?

My brain tends to work differently when I see other responsibilities pushed into separate objects. Then, I focus only on the behavior of the class I’m reading, since the objects I’m delegating to cannot affect anything more than what I pass to them. I can quickly grasp the behaviors my class expects from its collaborators and instantly tell whether the responsibility of the class is fulfilled well or not. For example, I don’t care what validation is - the only thing I know is that I need to call it and it will just “handle stuff”.

As a side note - there are some people that hate design patterns and say that they hurt readability. While I agree that “pattern religion” is bad, I have actually seen many, many, many situations, when using design patterns enhanced readability, because they would just “fit in” into the solution. E.g. when I want to add tracing of every method call made against an object, a decorator is an obvious choice. Then, looking at the decorator, one can instantly see that the intention of the code is to provide tracing over a method call - it doesn’t have to be digged for.

Ok, that’s everything I have for today. Feel free to comment with your thoughts!

This post is about how TDD informs analysis and stimulates learning. We’ll go through a simple example and investigate rationale and mechanics of decisions taken.

The boards starts empty

Let’s imagine we’re writing a virtual Kanban-like board (this is also called a ‘scrum board’ AFAIK). If you don’t know what a scrum board is: the board is used for task tracking and is split into vertical columns that represent task progress (like NOT STARTED, IN PROGRESS, DONE). It’s also split into horizontal categories that represent bigger units of work (often user stories) that the tasks belong to. We usually add a task to the story and watch it pass through the vertical columns until we reach the DONE state.You can read more on scrum boards if you’re unfamiliar with the topic, however, what I’ve written here is enough knowledge to push forward with our example.

There is only one issue: how to start? We could do proper requirements analysis or commonality-variability analysis or something along the way, but this time, let’s just start by writing a spec (AKA unit test). What’s the simplest behavior we can come up with? Let’s see… it would be:

The board should start off as empty.

This is written in plain English (we’ll investigate another notation in a second), but that’s enough to get us started. Using the above statement, we can put together the first spec:

[Test]
public void ShouldStartOffClean ()
{
  var board = new ScrumBoard ();
  Assert.IsTrue (board.IsEmpty);
}

The first time I wrote this spec, it seemed (wrongly, but that’s coming in a minute :-)) silly to me. Why? Because:

It didn’t let me discover any new collaboration and any new abstraction other than ScrumBoard, which I already knew I was going to need.
It verifies a public flag is set on the same object that is specified. It looks like cheating - we consider X did something when it tells us so
It’s only a flag, nothing more. No domain logic is needed to implement it
I can’t imagine this flag used anywhere in the application. Even when I write a GUI that displays the board, it’s unlikely that it’s gonna need to check whether the board is empty. In Scrum board domain, empty board is not a special condition of any kind and does not trigger any special behaviors or conditions.

So, did we just waste our time here?

Negative learning

Let’s hold our horses for a minute before deleting this spec and try to write this spec in a Given-When-Then form:

GIVEN nothing

WHEN a new scrum board is created

THEN it should be empty

The Given-When-Then form has this nice capability that you can discover many things by simply negating what you already have (by the way, this is not the only way to proceed, but this is the one I want to show you). We can be smart about it, but for now, I suggest we take the brute force approach - we’ll go through each part of the behavior description and try to negate everything we can. We expect to run into some VERY obvious conclusions as well as find some jewels.

Assumptions: Given nothing

Here, we can make only one negation in the following form:

GIVEN NOT nothing

What is “not nothing”? It’s “something” :-). What can we learn from it? Not much. In fact, most of the app logic we’re going to write will rely on assumption that “there is something”. Nothing valuable, let’s move on

Trigger: When a new scrum board is created

Let’s start with negating the second part (the order doesn’t matter, it’s just that this part is more obvious):

WHEN a new scrum board is NOT created

What does it mean that the scrum board is not created? It’s the central abstraction of our domain, so what’s the point in not creating it? This may lead to a question: Is a scrum board the right abstraction? Maybe it would be more valuable to look at it as “a process”, not “a place”? I such case, a better abstraction would be “sprint” (which is represented by the board on the GUI level), not board. Let’s assume we decided to leave the “board” abstraction (although this thought is so valuable, that I’d probably add it to my TODO list to be able to revise my decision as the development goes on).

A nice thought from such a stupid negation, don’t you think? Ok, let’s dig further by negating the first part:

WHEN a NOT new scrum board is created

What does it mean “NOT a new board”? I means “an old board”. Wait a minute, that’s INTERESTING! Let’s ask further question: what does it mean to “create an old board”? It rings a bell - it’s about “loading an old board”. Wait a minute! This is a perfectly valid use case, because no user would like the board to disappear when they turn off the app! As this is not the core functionality, while not letting our self esteem and enthusiasm about this discovery eat us, we add it to the TODO list for later and proceed with the next negation.

Outcome: Then it should be empty

Again, there is only one negation we can perform:

THEN it should NOT be empty

We thought knowing that the board is empty doesn’t help the app at all. But what about us? Does it help us learn anything? Let’s check it out by asking further question: when is the board not empty? The answer: when there is at least one task added. Yes, we discovered the next use case - adding a task. This looks like the next core functionality element we need!

Let’s document this discovery with a Given-When-Then form:

GIVEN an empty board

WHEN a new task is added to it

THEN it should not be empty

And an executable specification:

[Test]
public void ShouldNotBeCleanWhenTaskIsAdded()
{
  var board = new ScrumBoard();
  var task = Any.InstanceOf<Task>();
  board.AddNew(task);
  Assert.IsFalse (board.IsEmpty);
}

Now THAT’S a discovery! Let’s quickly recap what we’ve learned here: we’ve learned that there is an abstraction called “Task” that can be added to the board by invoking the “AddNew()” method (which needs to be implemented: another item for the TODO list!). We’ve also got another Given-When-Then behavior description that we can analyze the same way as the first one. Shhh… I’ll tell you a secret: until now we’ve been proceeding asking question “What if not?”. Another useful question to ask is “What else?”, and we can apply it to the WHEN part by asking “What else happens when we add a task?”. But that’s another story.

Summary

What I tried to show you is how TDD can be often used to inform analysis. I’ve also tried to show how potentially pointless specs can help us learn more on our domain or ask the right questions about the domain. I’m not trying to say that TDD is a substitute for other analysis methods, such as commonality-variability analysis, but it sure adds much to your current toolset.

Ok, that’s it, time for a walk :-). Bye!

Hi, today, I’d like to outline few differences between a technique called Programming By Intention and Test-Driven Development. I’m currently halfway through Essential Skills For The Agile Developer and the chapter on Programming By Intention made me revisit this fine technique and think it over again, especially in comparison to Test-Driven Development.

What’s Programming By Intention?

On the book’s page you can get the chapter on Programming By Intention for free and read it, but for those of you that like summaries - it’s an outside-in approach to writing methods, that makes a distinction between so called “Sergeant” methods and “Private” methods. A “Sergeant” is a method that has the single responsibility of describing a high-level workflow and it delegates all the implementation details to “Private” methods. When beginning to write a piece of code, you start with a “Sergeant” and pretend that all the methods it needs to call already exist (although they usually don’t). A simplified example of a “sergeant” for logging-in logic would be something like this:

public string LogIn(string userName, string password)
{
  string homePage = GetHomePageAddress();
  string loginPage = GetLoginPageAddress();
  string response = GetDefaultResponse();

  if(AreCredentialsValid(userName, password))
  {
    response = GetResponseWithSuccessfulLoginMessage();
    RedirectTo(homePage);
  }
  else
  {
    response = GetResponseWithLoginErrorsFor(userName);
    RedirectTo(loginPage);
  }
  return response;
}

As you can see, in the above example, we’re passing what we can as method parameters instead of relying on fields. Also, there are almost no operators (even “new” and object access operator “.”) - they’re hidden inside the “private” methods to whom we delegate the work. These methods don’t exist yet - we’re just imagining how they should look to fit our needs. The next step is to generate skeleton bodies for “privates” (preferably using an IDE) and fill them in one by one (Of course, a “private” for this method might also be a “sergeant” with its own “privates”). A simple implementation example of a private method might look like this:

private string GetResponseWithLoginErrorsFor(string userName)
{
  return userName + " could not login. Invalid credentials";
} 

Programming By Intention produces code that is very readable - every work-flow step has its domain-specific name. Also, this technique is so powerful, because it separates specification perspective from implementation perspective and, by doing so, leads to a very high method cohesion. Thus, for example, it’s very simple to refactor our exemplary “sergeant” later into something like this:

public Response LogIn(
  UserCredentials userCredentials,
  Page homePage, 
  Page loginPage)
{
  Response response = Response.Default();

  if(credentials.AreValid())
  {
    response.SetUpWithSuccessfulLoginMessage();
    homePage.RedirectTo();
  }
  else
  {
    response.SetUpWithLoginErrorsFor(userName);
    loginPage.RedirectTo();
  }
  return response;
}

and achieve class-level cohesion, although the decision whether to pay that cost right now or defer it for later is left to us. Thanks to this, Programming By Intention can be at best almost no-cost (in case of small programs that don’t need any maintenance in the future), while at worst allowing us to defer the cost for later while introducing minimal technical debt (in case of more serious pieces of software that need cohesion on every level).

How does it relate to Test-Driven Development?

I must confess that this is the second most powerful technique I know for writing good and easy to read code, the only more powerful being Test-Driven Development. Whenever I am in a situation where for some reasons I cannot use TDD, I use Programming by Intention.

Now, let’s examine the similarities between the two techniques first:

Both are outside-in approaches (I’m talking here about the outside-in style of TDD, as it can also be used bottom-up, as e.g. Kent Beck prefers to use it), crafting APIs and method names from the perspective of their use
Both are variants of the divide-and-conquer strategy
Both are about specifying intention through code
Both tend to lead to highly cohesive designs, although TDD demands both class-level and method-level cohesion, while Programming By Intention tends to demand method-level cohesion only (although class-level is easily achievable from there, as in the example above).

Now for the differences. The main one in my opinion is that Programming By Intention looks at writing code from a perspective of a method, while Test-Driven Development looks from the perspective of a behavior. This means several things:

When implementing a single method (as in Programming By Intention), one does not see the whole context of its usage - only this one method. On the other hand, in TDD, when writing a unit-level spec, it usually begins with object instantiation and ends with observable result (either returning a result or call collaborating object’s method)
The method perspective also means that, when writing it using Programming By Intention, one has to consider the method as a whole - e.g. all required execution paths (ifs and elses) must be considered throughout the whole implementation process, since they’re all usually added in one go. On the other hand, in TDD one only worries about the current path he’s specifying with a test. Other paths are either already tied to other tests that will remind us when we unintentionally break them (so we don’t have to think about them anymore), or on our TODO list (so we don’t have to worry about them yet).

The second point is, IMHO, really important. Few days ago, I finally watched a presentation by Gojko Adzic and Dan North from BDD Exchange. Talking about accelerating Agile, Gojko and Dan stressed very heavily the importance of making a “measurable impact”. I think that, when scaled down, this idea aligns well with TDD. The “measurability” of the “impact” we make with our executable specifications can be considered in two ways:

For a single specification: watching the RED to GREEN transition is an act of measuring the impact - reaching the GREEN phase means that you now have something that was not present yet during the RED phase.
For a suite of specifications: the comparison of already implemented specs vs the ones left on the TODO list are a way to measure “how much of the impact” was already made vs what’s left.

Summary

Personally, I find many similarities between Programming By Intention and TDD, with Programming By Intention being lower cost (at least in the short run) and easier to learn, while TDD being more powerful and advanced. I dare to say that TDD is Programming By Intention on steroids. Also, I believe that learning Programming By Intention helps in in grasping mock-based Test Driven Development. Hence, if you are struggling with outside-in TDD using mocks, it’s a good idea to train Programming By Intention first.

That’s all for today, I hope you liked it and see you soon!

Welcome to part 2 of my post about TDD objections.

By the way, I found an interesting analysis on slideshare on the same topic. It’s an interesting read, so be sure to take a look.

Where did we leave the last time?

Ok, let’s take on the next set of objections from the list:

Not enough time
TDD will slow us down, because we’ll have to create a lot of additional code
TDD will slow us down, because we’ll have to maintain a lot of additional code
We don’t have the necessary skills or experience
We don’t have the necessary tools
(This one is unit testing specific) There are already other kinds of tests, we don’t need unit tests?
It’s very hard to perform with legacy code
I already know how to write a testable code, TDD will not really improve my design
We’ve got enough quality and we’re doing fine without TDD
My manager won’t let me do TDD
There’s no “scientific proof” and enough research on whether TDD really provides a return of investment

The ones I’m gonna talk about today are the one marked with strong text. Let’s go then!

4. We don’t have the necessary skills or experience

This is a valid impediment. However, its a common one in any skill. You see, it’s an extremely rare situation that someone is proficient using a technique for the first time (think of the times when you learned how to use a keyboard and a mouse). Most techniques require some time and knowledge to master - the same is with TDD. Let’s say that TDD is like a flower, where the core is the “Red-Green-Refactor” cycle and there are a lot of petals - good practices and heuristics. These include: need-driven design, triangulation, mocking, listening to tests etc.

Thankfully, lack of skills can be dealt with by providing training, mentoring, books, doing katas, randoris and by the teams drawing conclusions out of their own experience. In other words, this is a temporary obstacle. Of course, together with staff rotation in your team comes the need to renew part of the investment in skills, knowledge and experience.

5. We don’t have the necessary tools

This too is a valid impediment. TDD is a kind of process that can be made a lot easier with tools. There are many areas where tools can improve the overall performance with TDD. These include:

Code navigation
Running unit tests
Automated refactoring
Code Analysis
Quick fixes (like “generate method signature from its use)
Continuous Testing
Code generation

…etc.

If the issue is “money related” (e.g. there are tools on the market, but hey have to be bought), then the management should consider buying the best tools that are on the market and are available within the company budget. Thus, it’s always good to have management buy-in for TDD. Thankfully, most of these tools (excluding the ones related to continuous testing) give a performance boost regardless of whether someone is using TDD or not, so many teams have such tools anyway.

If the issue is “technology related” (there are no tools on the market that work well with the technology your team is using), the good news is that TDD is usable even without these tools and still provides a lot of its benefits, since it is about analysis, design and specification. The tools only (well, “only” :-)) help in keeping focus and go faster through the whole cycle.

6. (This one is unit testing specific) There are already other kinds of tests, we don’t need unit tests?

Although TDD is not solely limited to unit-level specs/tests, they form a crucial part of it. While some people believe that we can skip higher level specs in TDD, there’s no one I know who says you can skip unit level.

Anyway, let’s get to the point. this objection is based on a premise that TDD is about testing and “unit tests” produced with it are merely another kinds of tests. When I hear people raising this argument, they talk a lot about coverage, defect discovery, strengthening the testing net etc. Such arguments, for the most part, miss the point, since they ignore the biggest benefits of TDD which do not lie in its testing aspect (which I already discussed).

Dealing with such objections is really hard, because it requires others to accept a different point of view than the one they kept believing in so far. Sure, the books and authorities are on your side, but hey, the guys that read books and listen to authorities don’t usually need convincing! So what to do in such case?

Remember, this argument is usually raised in teams that don’t even do unit testing, let alone TDD. The following options are available:

Point the opponents to the blog posts and literature - be careful with this. If you do it wrong, the other side may take it as questioning their professionalism. Also, they may just question the authorities you believe in - this is rather easy in software engineering world - they can just say “that doesn’t convince me at all” and the game is over. You have to somehow show that you’re passionate about TDD and point at such sources as to something that made you passionate. In other words, if you want to lead someone out of their biases, tell them that you too were led out before them and tell them how. This leaves them in a position of “look, there’s a way to do things better” instead of “you’re all idiots and only I know the truth”. I’m hardly an expert on this matter, however, there are some “change patterns” that are worth checking out.
Talk about your experiences from your previous projects if you have any or bring someone else if you don’t. There are not many arguments as convincing as “I have experienced it myself”, especially to the guys that don’t have any experience in a certain field and are in a process of evaluating whether it makes sense to enter this field. Also, some people are more convinced by “soft” arguments (“we did it like this before and everybody in the team said that they feel in improvement in their coding style as never before”), while others are better convinced by “hard” arguments (“we did it like this before and we were able to get the best results of code complexity analysis in the whole project plus we were able to demonstrate a print out of documentation of 40 pages that just came out for free as we did TDD.”). Also, better than words are living proofs (“you can just ask those guys I worked with and they show you what our living documentation looks like” or “Just ask the guys that were there with me on how they feel about it”).
Create an internal training. This has one big advantage and two small disadvantages. The advantage is that you have a lot of time (at least longer than on regular meetings) to lead people by hand through your argumentation, reasons, examples and so on. In other words, you’re given a chance to give more full explanation of the idea. The first disadvantage is that usually you get to prepare for such training in your free time (since management usually approves only spending time on giving the training, not on preparing it). The second disadvantage is that the people that you want to convince can simply ignore the invitation to the training and not attend at all or (if they’re forced to attend) they can spend the whole training doing their stuff on their laptops.

7. It’s very hard to perform with legacy code

The version of this objection that I find valid is: “It’s harder to perform with legacy code”. Why? Because TDD requires the code to have a quality called “testability”. Legacy code doesn’t usually have it. Thus, the code has to be refactored, risking breaking something that already works (if you know how to do this, then the risk is significantly lower, but there’s still some risk). On the other hand, there is this temptation to just “insert a little if clause right in the middle of this mess and be done with”.

Anyway, the strategy to deal with this objection is to somehow make is clear that it’s either “we don’t have the necessary skills” or “we don’t have the necessary tools” objection, just dressed differently. In the first case, take a look at the following books:

Refactoring by Martin Fowler
Dealing Effectively With Legacy Code by Michael Feathers
Behead Your Legacy Beast. Refactor and Restructure Relentlessly With The Mikado Method (free e-book) by Daniel Brolund and Ola Ellnestam

and in the second case, talk to your boss and make sure that your team has the tools it needs.

Part 3 is already published! Go ahead and read it!

In the meantime, I’ll be happy to hear your comments. I’m not an oracle and would gladly learn more about what objections do people receive and how they dispel them.

This post is going to be mostly about seeing TDD in a larger picture and is mostly inspired by some materials by Ken Pugh on Acceptance Test Driven Development (although it does not exactly echo Ken’s opinions).

What is a requirement?

Imagine you’ve got technical requirements, one of which looks like this:

All incoming e-mail messages that are directed to recipient called emergency@my.mail.com shall be broadcasted to all accounts in the my.mail.com domain

Here, the technical requirement defines a special emergency e-mail address that may be used as a kind of emergency notification mechanism (like when an error occurs on your website). What’s usually expected from the development team is to take this requirement and implement, so that the requirement is fulfilled. In other words, this is a request to perform an amount of work.

But how do you know that this amount of work needs to be performed? How do you know that you need to state such a requirement and send it to the development team?

Let’s stop for a minute and consider these questions. Thinking about it, we can arrive at the following hypothetical situations:

A customer (be it business representative or real end-user) is familiar with another system, where such notification mechanism worked and worked well. Going to our system, he expects it to have a similar functionality. However, in a situation when he expects an emergency to be communicated to all staff, nothing happens.
A customer is familiar with our system and knows what it can and cannot do. He comes up with an idea that having such feature would greatly increase visibility of website errors, and recognizes that up to now, the system does not implement it.
A customer not familiar with our system reads a user manual and discovers that this kind of functionality, which he knows he’ll need, is not described in there, so looks like it does not exist.
A customer is about to buy our system and as one of the feature he wants the system to support, he mentions emergency notification solution, but the sales representative tells him that the system does not support this kind of functionality

Test-first

We can imagine that one of the situations described above may have led to this new requirement being specified. But what are these situations? Let’s try to rephrase them a little, adding a small comment in braces after each one that should clear the situation a bit:

A customer leads to a situation where he expects everybody to be notified of the emergency situation, but they’re not notified (FAIL).
A customer searches his memory expecting to find the fact that our system implements the feature, but cannot find the fact because it’s not true (FAIL).
A customer expects the user manual to contain information that such a feature exists, but the manual says that it doesn’t (FAIL).
A customer expects the sales representative to tell him that their system supports the desired feature, but the representative tells him otherwise (FAIL)

Yes, you’ve guessed it - these are tests! Well, maybe not JUnit/NUnit/Rspec/whateverUnit tests, but they’re tests anyway. What’s more, they’re tests that fail, which makes us “repair” this “failure” by providing a technical requirement and then implementing it.

What got lost?

Also, note that the tests tell nothing about e-mail and the broadcast address - they tell us that our customer expects everybody to be notified of emergency situation. The e-mail part is what’s been added in the requirement. At the same time, another piece of information was dropped by translating test into technical requirement - the user’s intention.

It’s because this requirement was HOW the user expectation should be satisfied.

The sad part is that, although these tests contain some information that got “lost in translation” to technical requirements, usually such tests are never even stored, not mentioning automating them (which, in some cases, could be possible).

There are two important lessons to learn from this story:

It’s a pity that we don’t value the tests that come before requirements
It’s a pity that we can’t see that tests come first. If we could, it would let us understand better why unit-level Test Driven Development makes perfect sense, because it’s the same process of specifying what we expect to have, seeing it not fulfilled and then providing it.

Ok, that’s it for today. Have fun!